A Guide to the Albemarle County (Va.) Wills, 1743-1928
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Albemarle County (Va.) Wills, 1743-1928
The Library of Virginia
1137994-1137999, 1140125-1140140, 1140174
10.35 cu. ft. (23 boxes)
Albemarle County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in transfer of court papers from Albemarle County.
Historical Information
Albemarle County was named for William Anne Keppel, second earl of Albemarle and governor of the Virginia colony from 1737 to 1754. It was formed from Goochland County in 1744, and part of Louisa County and certain islands in the Fluvanna River, now called the James, were added in 1761 and 1838.
Individuals dying with a written will died testate. After the death of an individual, his or her will was brought into court, where two of the subscribing witnesses swore that the document was genuine. After the will was proved, the executor was bonded to carry out his or her duties to settle the estate. The court then ordered the will to be recorded.
Scope and Content
Albemarle County (Va.) Wills, 1778-1908, record the deceased's plan for how his or her estate was to be divided among his or her heirs following his or her death. Information commonly recorded in wills include the name of the deceased, also referred as the testator; names of heirs; a listing of real and personal property (including slaves) and how it was to be divided among the heirs; names of individuals who were to be the will's executors; the date will was written; and the date will was recorded at the court house. Additional record types may be found in this collection such as fiduciary records (inventories and accounts.)
Arrangement
Chronological
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Albemarle County Will Books can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm
Albemarle County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Albemarle County Court Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the Lost Records Localities Database found at the Library of Virginia web site.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Albemarle County (Va.) Circuit Court
Subjects:
African Americans -- History; Estates (Law) -- Virginia -- Albemarle County; Land subdivision -- Virginia -- Albemarle County; Slaveholders -- Virginia -- Albemarle County; Slaves -- Virginia -- Albemarle County
Geographical Names:
Albemarle County -- History
Genre and Form Terms:
Local government records -- Virginia -- Albemarle County; Wills -- Virginia -- Albemarle County
Contents List
- Wills 1778-1790 (Barcode 1137994)
- Wills 1791-1799 (Barcode 1137995)
- Wills 1800-1806 (Barcode 1137996)
- Wills 1806-1813 (Barcode 1137997)
- Wills 1814-1820 (Barcode 1137998)
- Wills 1821-1827 (Barcode 1137999)
- Wills 1828-1833 (Barcode 1140125)
- Wills 1833-1839 (Barcode 1140126)
- Wills 1840-1845 (Barcode 1140127)
- Wills 1845-1848 (Barcode 1140128)
- Wills 1849-1852 (Barcode 1140129)
- Wills 1852-1856 (Barcode 1140174)
- Wills 1857-1859 (Barcode 1140130)
- Wills 1860-1864 (Barcode 1140131)
- Wills 1864-1869 (Barcode 1140132)
- Wills 1869-1873 (Barcode 1140133)
- Wills 1874-1877 (Barcode 1140134)
- Wills 1878-1881 (Barcode 1140135)
- Wills 1882-1885 (Barcode 1140136)
- Wills 1886-1890 (Barcode 1140137)
- Wills 1891-1894 (Barcode 1140138)
- Wills 1894-1898 (Barcode 1140139)
- Wills 1898-1908 (Barcode 1140140)